<tool name="Submit Contrast Dataset" id="confero_platform_submit_contrast_dataset" version="0.1">
    <description>to the Confero DB and compute and store gene sets</description>
    <command interpreter="perl">
        ../bin/cfo_run_cmd.pl $cmd 
        --data-file=$contrast_file 
        --data-type="$data_type"
        #if $id_type.value != "?"
        --id-type="$id_type"
            #if $id_type.value == "GeneSymbol" and $organism.value != "?"
        --organism="$organism"
            #end if
        #end if
        --orig-filename="$contrast_file.name" 
        --report-file=$report 
        --report-as-html
        --no-processed-file-output
        --collapsing-method=$collapsing_method
        #if $cmd.value == False
        --dataset-name="$dataset_name" 
        --dataset-desc="$dataset_desc" 
            #if $overwrite_existing.value == True
        --overwrite-existing
            #end if
            #if $skip_threshold_checks.value == True
        --skip-threshold-checks
            #end if
        #end if
    </command>
    <inputs>
        <param name="contrast_file" type="data" format="cfocontrastdataset" label="Contrast Dataset File to Check, Process and Submit"/>
        <param name="id_type" type="select" force_select="false" optional="true" label="Contrast Dataset IDs From" dynamic_options="cfo_get_info('id_types', True)">
            <help>OPTIONAL: select ID type if not already set in data file header</help>
        </param>
        <param name="organism" type="select" force_select="false" optional="true" label="Organism" dynamic_options="cfo_get_info('organisms', True)">
            <help>OPTIONAL: select organism if your IDs are gene symbols (i.e. #%id_type=GeneSymbol) AND organism not already set in data file header</help>
        </param>
        <!-- Galaxy doesn't yet support dynamic_options controlling conditionals
        <conditional name="id_type_cond">
            <param name="id_type" type="select" force_select="false" optional="true" label="Contrast Dataset IDs From" dynamic_options="cfo_get_info('id_types', True)"/>
            <when value="EntrezGene"/>
            <when value="GeneSymbol">
                <param name="organism" type="select" force_select="false" optional="true" label="Organism" dynamic_options="cfo_get_info('organisms', True)"/>
            </when>
        </conditional>
        -->
        <param name="dataset_name" type="text" size="100" label="Dataset Name">
            <help>OPTIONAL: specify dataset name if not already set in data file header or you don't want to use file base name as dataset name</help>
        </param>
        <param name="dataset_desc" type="text" area="true" size="5x100" label="Dataset Description">
            <help>OPTIONAL: specify dataset description if not already set in data file header.  Please do not put manual carriage returns in the text area</help>
        </param>
        <param name="collapsing_method" type="select" label="Collapsing Method">
            <option value="contrast_data">contrast data</option>
            <option value="dataset_data">dataset data</option>
        </param>
        <param name="cmd" type="boolean" truevalue="process_data_file" falsevalue="process_submit_data_file" checked="false">
            <label>Process and Check Contrast Dataset Only</label>
            <help>
            Check this if you want to only check and map your contrast dataset file and review the report but not submit anything to the Confero database
            </help>
        </param>
        <param name="overwrite_existing" type="boolean">
            <label>Overwrite Any Existing Dataset</label>
            <help>
            Check this if you want to force overwrite of all data for any existing contrast dataset in the database with the same name
            </help>
        </param>
        <param name="skip_threshold_checks" type="boolean">
            <label>Skip Gene Set Threshold Checks</label>
            <help>
            Check this if you want to skip any threshold checks on computed gene sets before submitting to Confero database
            </help>
        </param>
        <param name="data_type" type="hidden" value="IdMAPS"/>
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data format="cforeporthtml" name="report" label="$tool.name on $on_string: $contrast_file.name"/>
    </outputs>
    <code file="common_functions.py"/>
    <help>
This tool will::

1. Check, process, map and collapse a source contrast dataset (idMAPSMAPSMAPS...) into an 
Entrez Gene ID-based contrast dataset using the latest source platform annnotations and NCBI Entrez Gene 
database.

2. Extracts gene sets from each contrast using parameters provided in the data file header or using 
Confero system defaults.

3. Submit dataset, contrasts, gene sets and all metadata into the Confero DB.

The tool provides a summary report of the procedure as output. 

If you do not have file to choose from in the Contrast Dataset File drop-down menu, it's because you have no files 
of this format in your Galaxy history.  You first need to do either one of the following::

  - Go to Get Data --> Upload File, select File Format: **cfocontrastdataset**, browse for and upload your idMAPS
  file.
  - Go to Upload LIMMA/SAM R Object, browse for and upload your limma/samr object file, then go to
  Convert LIMMA/SAM R Object and convert the object into an idMAPS file and adding the request header fields.

IMPORTANT INFORMATION::

* All the contrasts in a file form a contrast dataset. Each individual contrast in the dataset is typically 
a experimental condition pairwise comparison or a linear model contrast matrix coefficient.

* The contrast dataset file can already be Entrez Gene ID-based, in this case the tool will check, 
process and update the IDs in your file using the latest NCBI Entrez Gene database.

* The contrast dataset file can exclude any or all of the M, P or S column(s) (idA, idAAA, idAMAMAM, 
idMAPMAPMAP) though it is highly recommended you have these.

* The contrast dataset file requires a data column header unless there is only one contrast in the dataset.

* All header metadata fields begin with a #% and have an = after the field name and before the field data. 
Field data with spaces must be quoted " ". Fields which accept multiple inputs need to be separated with
a comma.  All header metadata fields must be at the top of the file, before any column header or data. 
Here is an example of a 4 contrast dataset::

  #%dataset_name="Adjuvant Tamoxifen Therapy"
  #%dataset_desc="The 76-gene signature defines high-risk patients that benefit from adjuvant tamoxifen therapy"
  #%id_type=HG-U133_Plus_2
  #%contrast_names="GSM305129","GSM305130","GSM305131","GSM305132"
  ID    A   M   P   S   A   M   P   S   A   M   P   S    A   M   P   S

* Various file header metadata fields are supported.  These currently are::

  - dataset_name
  - dataset_desc
  - contrast_names [multi]
  - gs_up_sizes [multi]
  - gs_dn_sizes [multi]
  - gs_p_val_thres [multi]
  - gs_m_val_thres [multi]
  - gs_a_val_thres [multi]
  - gs_data_split_meths [multi]
  - gs_min_size
  - gs_max_size
  - id_type
  - organism (specify only gene symbols are your IDs (#%id_type=GeneSymbol) Confero will automatically 
determine organism for all other ID types)

* Various additional annotation metadata fields are supported.  These currently are::

  - system
  - study_no
  - cell_tissue
  - stimulus

* If the metadata header dataset_name is not included, the basename of the file will be used for 
the dataset name.

* For multi-contrast dataset files, the metadata header **contrast_names** is required.  For single-contrast 
dataset files, if the metadata header does not exist the uploaded contrast file basename will be used.

* If you already have certain metadata fields in your file header then you should skip using the OPTIONAL 
web form menus to specify these fields.
    </help>
</tool>

